またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
The human hat is still here.
まだある 人間のぼうし
還在這裡啊 人類的帽子
It's all white and pretty, like snow.
白くて綺麗　雪みたい
白白的真好看 像雪一樣
誰も拾ってくれないの
沒有人要你嗎
No one will pick you up?
だったら家に来る？
那就來我家吧
Want to come home with me?
綺麗 母様に見せよ
真漂亮 給媽媽看看吧
It's so pretty.
I'm going to show mom.
Mom...
母様
媽媽
No, I can't be crying when I'm going to grow up!
男子たるものがめそめそと
男子漢可不能哭哭啼啼的
これからは一人で生きていくのだ
以後還要一個人生活下去的
From now on, I have to live on my own!
The Little Fox's Hat
行ってきます 塔子さん
我走了 塔子阿姨
I'm going now, Touko-san.
気をつけて 楽しんできてね
路上小心 玩得開心哦
Take care and have fun.
はい
好
I will.
Takashi.
貴志
Yes?
はい
是
勉強合宿で雁羽温泉へ行くそうだね
補習合宿要去雁羽溫泉吧
You're going to the hot spring
reserve on your study trip, right?
うん はい
嗯 是的
Yes.
I'm sorry for having you pay for the trip.
すいません 合宿の費用を出していただいて
抱歉 還讓你們付了合宿的費用
そんなことは気にしなくてもいい
不用在意那個
You don't need to worry about that.
I just have a small favor to ask of you.
ちょっと頼みことがあるんだ
我有事要拜託你
There's a pottery in the mountains near the hot springs,
温泉近くの山にある窯元で茶碗を受け取ってきてくれないか
能幫我從溫泉附近的山窯那裡把茶碗取回來嗎
so could you pick up some tea cups for me?
I received a call saying that they were almost done.
もうすぐ出来上がると連絡があったんでね
那邊跟我聯絡說就快要做好了
Could I ask you to do this?
頼めるかな
拜託你啦
もちろんです 滋さん
沒問題 滋叔
Of course, Shigeru-san.
What a weird laugh, Natsume.
不気味な笑いだな 夏目
笑得我毛骨悚然啊 夏目
Sensei, when did you get in?
あ 先生 何時の間に
老師 你什麼時候…
用心棒がついてくるのは当然だろう
我這個保鏢當然得跟著你了
Isn't it natural for your bodyguard to follow you?
そうだけど
話雖然這麼說…
That's true, but...
So, what are you so happy about?
で 何がそんなに嬉しいのだ
話說 什麼事讓你這麼開心
嬉しいものなんだな
所謂開心事啊
It feels good to be asked to do a favor for someone else.
誰かから何かを頼まれるって
就是有人拜託你去做某件事
[Sign: Kariwa Hot Springs Ko-nai High School Camp.]
Great people will eventually meet their ruin,
たけき者も遂には滅びぬ
害人者終將走向末路
much like dust before the wind.
ひとへに風の前の塵に同じ
就像風前塵土
All right, let's end the morning class here.
よし 午前中はここまでにするか
好了 上午就到這裡了
昼飯まで自由時間だ
中飯之前是自由時間
You have a break until lunch.
All right! What should we do?
よしゃー さて 何する
太好了 接下來要做什麼
We've got to go to the hot spring first!
先ずは温泉だろう 温泉
先去溫泉 溫泉
な 夏目
是吧 夏目
Right, Natsume?
Sorry, I have some business to take care of.
悪い 俺ちょっと有事あるから
抱歉 我還有點事
あ そうなの
是嗎
Oh, really?
Ah, I'm sure it's in this area.
えっと たぶんこの辺だと思うんだけど
那個 大概就在這附近了吧
Ah, over there.
あそこか
那邊嗎
Hey, you weak little fox!
弱虫のちび狐
你這無能的小狐狸
You're still hanging around the forest?
まだ森をウロチョロしてんのか
還在森林裡亂轉啊
You're an eyesore, you useless brat!
役立たずは目障りなんだよ
無能的傢伙還真是礙眼
この この この
蠢貨 蠢貨
Leave the forest, you useless brat!
森から出て行け役立たず
給我滾出森林 你這個廢物
この このこの
蠢貨 蠢貨
Useless brat?
役立たず？
無能
Leave!
出て行けっつっとんや
給我滾出去
Stop!
止めろ
住手
W-Who is he?
誰
是誰
What are you doing bullying this little child?
何やってんだお前達
你們在幹什麼
こんな小さな子をいじめて
居然欺負這麼小的孩子
Are you a human child?
きさま 人の子か
你這傢伙 是人類？
How dare a human child look down on us!
人のこのくせに我らを甘く見るとは
人類居然敢小看我們
How impetuous! I'll kill you!
生意気な
真是囂張
食ろうてやろう
看我吃了你
Oh well.
まあいっか
算了
You're a real busybody as always, Natsume.
相変わらずおせっかいだな 夏目
夏目你還真是一如既往的 愛管閒事
仕方ないだろう
沒辦法嘛
It couldn't be helped.
しかし とんだ無駄あしだったわ
可是 今天算白來了
Still, what a waste of time.
また出直さねばならんとは
必須下次再來了
We have to come back again.
仕方がないさ
我也沒辦法呀
It can't be helped, the tea cups won't be finished baking until tomorrow.
茶碗が焼きあがるのは明日だって言うんだから
因為茶碗明天才能燒好
Humans are such troublesome creatures.
人間とは面倒くさい生き物だな
人類還真是麻煩的生物
たかが食い物を入れるだけの器皿
不過是盛放食物的器皿
They go so far for just a food container,
yet they could just buy it at the local super market.
近くのスーパー辺で買えばよかろうが
在附近的超市里打發了不就好了
You're being brutally frank saying that.
それをいったら 身も蓋もないだろ
你這麼說就沒品位了啊…
A body isn't a container, though.
身は器じゃないだろう
身體又不是容器
What are you talking about?
何言ってんだ
說什麼呢
人間は嫌い だけど
我討厭人類 可是
I hate humans,
but...
Natsume, it's going your way!
夏目 行ったぞ
夏目 接球
All right, all right!
オーライ オーライ
來吧
Nice!
ナイス
漂亮
Natsume, don't sleep.
夏目 寝るな
夏目 給我醒醒
Natsume...
夏目…
It bounced off you and hit me earlier.
先夏目君の流れ弾に当たったのよ
剛才被扔給夏目的流彈誤傷了哦
あ ごめんごめん
抱歉 抱歉
Sorry, sorry.
I wonder what dinner will be, right, Natsume?
晩飯なんだろうな 夏目
晚飯是什麼呢 夏目
Yeah, I'm looking forward to it.
あ 楽しみだな
嗯 我也很期待
夏目はよく笑う
夏目很愛笑
Natsume laughs often,
でもなんか嘘っぽい
但是像是假裝的一樣
but it seems kind of fake.
言葉も 仕草も 気配も
說話也好 動作也好 態度也好
His words, his gestures, his aura,
どこか嘘っぽい
總感覺不真實
they all seem kind of fake.
本当は人間じゃないのかも
或許他並不是人類
Maybe he's not really a human.
Maybe he's like me and is disguised as a human.
本当は僕と同じで人間に化けてて
只是像我一樣 變幻成人類的樣子
Maybe he's lonely like me.
僕と同じ一人ぼっちで
其實 他和我一樣獨自一人
だったら一緒にこの森に住んでくれたらいいのに
所以 我來邀請他和我一起在森林裡生活吧
He should live in the forest with me, then!
ねえ 母様
好嗎 媽媽
Right, mom?
[Sign: Kariwa Hot Springs.]
Damn, I'm going back tomorrow,
まいったな
麻煩了
明日には家へ帰るし
我明天就要回家
妙ななつき方したら かわいそうだ
他要是喜歡上我 那就太可憐了
and I'd feel bad if it got attached to me.
It's too late.
もう遅いわ
已經遲了哦
うるさいぞ 先生
你真囉唆 老師
Shut up, sensei.
ちょー最悪
今天真倒楣
This is the worst.
We can't go get the tea cups now.
これは茶碗を取りに行くどころじゃないよ
現在也不能去拿茶碗了
授業までに戻れるかどうか
上課之前能不能趕回去都是個問題
Who knows if we can even make it back to class now.
Natsume-dono.
夏目殿
夏目大人
空耳か
幻聽嗎
Am I just hearing things?
Thank you.
ありがとう
謝謝你
Mom, I'm useful now.
母様 僕に役に立てましたよ
媽媽 我也有些用處了喲
ありがとうって
有人對我說謝謝呢
He said "Thank you" to me.
もう役立たずじゃありませんよね
我不再一無是處了
I'm not useless anymore, right?
明日はきのこをとろう
明天去採蘑菇吧
I'll go gather mushrooms tomorrow.
いっぱいとって 夏目に分けてやろう
多採一點 分給夏目一些
I'll gather a lot and share some with Natsume!
Oh, you're still here, you little fox?
おや ちび狐
哎呀 小狐狸
まだいやがったか
還在這裡啊
懲りないやつだな
真是學不乖呢
She just doesn't learn.
We told you to get lost!
失せろって言ったろ
不是叫你消失嗎
この この この
臭小子 臭小子…
この森には役立たずはいらねえんだよ この
這個森林裡不需要你這種一無是處的傢伙
We don't need any useless brats in this forest!
You're wrong!
違う もう役立たずじゃない
不是的 我有用的
I'm not useless anymore!
くそ いたたたた
該死 痛痛…
Damn it!
こいつ
這傢伙
I'll kill you, you little brat!
このちび 許さんぞ
小不點 我不會放過你的
I told you to stop!
止めろって言っただろう
不是讓你們住手了嗎
こいつは…
這傢伙是…
Damn him!
The one from yesterday!
昨日の
昨天的
Were my fists not enough for you?
げんこつじゃ足りないってのか
拳頭還不夠讓你們長記性嗎
Natsume-dono...
夏目殿 夏目殿
夏目大人 夏目大人
Natsume-dono!
Who is it?
誰だ
是誰
Have you forgotten, Natsume Reiko-dono?
お忘れですか 夏目レイコ殿
您忘了嗎 夏目玲子大人
You said you would come and return my name in the spring.
春が来たなら
不是說到了春天
名前をお返しくださるとおしゃったではありませんか
就把名字還給我嗎
レイコめ相変わらず罪作りなことよ
玲子還真是到處惹事
Damn Reiko, she's as cruel as always.
Spring? How many springs have passed already?
春って もう何度目の春なんだよ
還說春天 都不知道過了多少個春天了
You're the one who called me?
あなたですか 呼んだのは
是你嗎 是你叫我嗎
Sensei, take care of the tea cups.
先生 茶碗を頼む
老師 茶碗就拜託你了
受け取れ 早蕨
請收下 早蕨
Take it, Sawarabi.
お前の名だ
你的名字
It's your name.
Eh, Natsume?!
夏目って あの友人帳の持ち主の
夏目是…那個友人帳的主人嗎
The owner of the Book of Friends?
Thank you for returning it.
確かにお返しいただきました
我已收下
The Book of Friends?
友人帳 聞いたことがある
友人帳 我聽說過
I've heard of it.
名前を書かれたものは主従の契約で結ばれると
只要被寫上名字 就會結下主從契約
When they have their names written in it, it serves as a contract and they are then bound to the owner.
名前取られる 逃げろ
名字會被拿走的 快跑
He'll take our names!
Run away!
何言ってんだ あいつら
那些傢伙說些什麼呢
What are they saying?
たった今名前を返したものが
剛剛歸還了名字的人
There's no way he'd take your names when he just returned one.
名前を奪うわけなかろうが
怎麼可能奪走他們的名字呢
僕の名前が書いてあります
這上面寫著我的名字
My name is written on it.
僕を子分にして下さい
讓我成為你的手下吧
Please make me your follower!
きっとお役に立ってみせます
我一定會派上用場的
I'm sure I'll be useful to you!
I don't need one.
いらないよ
不需要哦
Is it because I'm weak?
僕が弱いから？
是因為我沒用嗎
僕なんか役に立たない？
是因為我一無是處嗎
Is it because I won't be useful?
こんなもので縛りあいたくない
我不想用這種東西束縛你
I don't want us to be bound like this.
僕達は親分子分の関係じゃない
我們之間不是主從關係
We aren't master and follower.
だろ
是吧
Right?
I think we have a different relationship.
もっと別の繋がりだと俺は思っているよ
我覺得一定有著其他的羈絆哦
My, what a wonderful color.
まあ 素敵な色だわ
哇 好漂亮的顏色
I'm going to change.
着替えてきます
我去換衣服
The townsfolk introduced me to a good pottery.
知人からいい窯元を紹介されてね
熟人介紹了一個好窯戶
家族が増えたのでこの際にと思ったんだ
剛好家庭成員又多了一個
Our family has grown, so I thought this was a good chance.
これが君のだ 貴志
這是你的 貴志
This is yours, Takashi.
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
謝謝你
It's just like that little fox said.
あの子狐に言った通りだ
就像我對小狐狸說的那樣
About what, Natsume?
何のことだ 夏目
你說什麼 夏目
役に立つ立たないじゃないんだ
不是有沒有用的問題
It's not about whether you're useful or useless.
I don't get it at all.
さっぱり分からん
搞不懂你說什麼
It really is pretty!
やっぱり綺麗
果然很漂亮
I want to show it to Natsume too.
夏目にも見せたいな
好想讓夏目也看看
Natsume...
夏目 夏目に会いたい
夏目 好想見夏目
I want to see Natsume.
I can't be crying when I'm going to grow up!
男子たるものがめそめそと
男子漢不能動不動就哭
強くなっていつか夏目の役に立つと決めたのだ
我決定了要變強大 這樣才能幫夏目的忙
I've already decided to become strong and to be helpful to Natsume!
Do you want to see Natsume that much?
そんなに夏目に会いたいか
那麼想見夏目嗎
I've heard the rumors.
うわさは聞いている
我聽到了傳聞
You met the owner of the Book of Friends, Natsume, didn't you?
お前友人帳を持つあの夏目と知り合ったそうだな
你和那個擁有友人帳的夏目成了朋友吧
You still can't disguise yourself as a human?
まだ人間に化けられないのか
你還不能化身為人嗎
If you can fill me up with fish, then I'll tell you a way to see Natsume.
もしわしに腹いっぱい魚を食わせてくれたら
如果你能讓我飽餐一頓魚
夏目に会える方法を教えてやってもいいぞ
我就告訴你怎麼去見夏目
Will you tell me how to see Natsume now?
これで夏目に会える方法を教えてくれる？
這樣的話 你就能告訴我去見夏目的方法了吧
ははは ばかな子狐だ
哈哈 傻狐狸
What a foolish little fox.
You were tricked.
騙されるとは
我只是騙你而已
You're always alone because you're so stupid.
そんなばかだからお前はいつも一人だった
就因為你這麼傻 至今才一個人
Natsume already forgot about you a long time ago.
夏目はお前のことなどとっくに忘れてるだろうさ
夏目恐怕早把你忘得一乾二淨了
Take this, little fox.
受け取れ 子狐
拿著吧 小狐狸
It's medicine that will allow you to become a human for one day.
一日だけ人間になれる薬だ
這是能變成人類一天的藥
Medicine to become a human?
人間になれる薬？
變成人的藥
If you want to see him, you can go see him yourself.
会いなければ自分から会いに行けばいい
如果想見 就去見他
That's all there is to it.
それだけの話だろう
就這麼簡單
That's right, I just have to go see him!
そうだ 会いに行けばいいんだ
是啊 想見他的話去見就好了
All right, I'm a fox too!
よし 僕だって狐のはしくれだ
搞定 我好歹也是狐狸
Once I go to the world of humans, I can follow Natsume's scent!
人間界に行けば夏目の匂いをたどれる
去人界的話應該能夠聞到夏目的味道
I'll be going now, mom.
行ってきます 母様
我走了 媽媽
夏目は一人で寂しがってないかな
夏目一個人會不會寂寞呢
I wonder if Natsume is feeling lonely being by himself.
Natsume's scent?
夏目の匂い
夏目的氣息
Natsume...
夏目 夏目の匂いは
夏目 夏目的氣息
It's Natsume's scent.
I want to see him!
会いたい
想見他
Hey, hey! Watch where you're going!
おらおら どこ見て歩いてんだよ
喂喂 看路啊
Where's Natsume?
夏目どこ
夏目在哪
Natsume?
夏目
あらあら 大丈夫 一人なの お母さんは
小朋友 你沒事吧 怎麼一個人 你媽媽呢
Oh, are you okay by yourself?
Where's your mother?
I'm fine by myself.
一人なんて平気
我一個人也沒問題的
I want to see him.
会いたい 会いたい
想見他 想見他
I want to see him!
どこ 夏目はどこ
在哪 夏目在哪
Where is he?
Where's Natsume?
Natsume!
夏目
There it is!
来た 引け引け
上鉤了 快拉
Pull it in! Pull it in!
It's huge!
でっかいな
好大
You again, Natsume?
また夏目かよ 大量じゃん
又是夏目 釣得真多啊
You caught a whole bunch.
悪いな
不好意思啦
Sorry.
What are you eating?
何食ってんだよ
你在吃什麼呢
It's Natsume's scent!
夏目の匂い いるんだ 近くに
夏目的氣息 找到了 就在附近
He's nearby!
I'll be able to see him!
会えるんだ
快見到了
焼けましたよ 貴志君のやまめ
烤好了喲 貴志釣的大馬哈魚
It's all fried!
It's the landlocked masu salmon Natsume caught!
おお これはこれは立派なやまめだ
噢 這魚可真大
Well, well, what a fine salmon you caught!
Let's eat, Takashi.
いただくよ 貴志
吃吧 貴志
はい
好
Okay.
貴志君は川魚大丈夫なのよね
貴志你不討厭河裡的魚呢
Yours has the skin, Takashi, so is that okay?
Yes, it's fine with me.
はい 僕は何でも
是的 我不挑食
苦手なものは遠慮なく言ってね
若是不喜歡一定要說哦
If you don't like anything, tell me, okay?
Shigure-san doesn't like green peppers.
滋さんはね ピーマンだめなのよ
滋叔他呀 不愛吃青椒
He's like a kid, right?
小さい子みたいでしょう
像個孩子似的
実は僕も小さい頃は苦手でした
其實我小時候也不太愛吃的
The truth is, when I was young, I didn't like them either.
そうか 味方ができたな ははは
是嗎 那我也算是有個同伴了
I see, so I've got someone I can relate with here too!
Here.
Let's see.
讓我嚐嚐看
Well, this salmon is pretty good, Touko-san.
いやー塔子さん このやまめなかなかいけますよ
塔子 這魚很不錯哦
じゃ 私もいただこうかな
那我也吃一點吧
Then maybe I'll have some too.
Go ahead.
どうぞどうぞ
吃吧吃吧
How is it?
どうですか
怎麼樣
うん 美味しい
嗯 很好吃啊
It's good!
うわー嬉しい こんな美味しいものいただいてね
能吃到這麼好吃的魚 真高興
That's great, Natsume looked like he was having fun!
よかった 夏目楽しそうだった
太好了 夏目看起來很開心
He wasn't lonely!
寂しくなんかなかった
一點都不寂寞
寂しいのは 寂しかったのは僕
寂寞的 寂寞的… 只有我
I...
I was the lonely one.
Wait!
待って
等等
So,
やっぱり あの時の子狐か
果然是那個時候的小狐狸啊
it was the little fox from before.
Thank you.
ありがとう 会いに来てくれたんだね
謝謝 你是來看我的吧
You came to see me, right?
You've got a cute hat.
可愛いぼうしだね
很可愛的帽子哦
嗯
Let's go have dinner and then I'll take you home.
ご飯食べて一緒に帰ろう
吃了晚飯一起回去吧
I have to remember the way.
道覚えなくちゃ
我得記住怎麼走
今度は俺が会いに行くよ
下次我去看你
I'll go see you next time.
嗯
Okay!
You're a good kid.
お前は偉いね
你很厲害呢
When I was lonely, I was afraid of going out.
俺は寂しくても踏み出すのが怖くて
我即使寂寞 也會害怕邁出腳步
I didn't even think of doing something about it.
なんとかしようなんて思わなかった
不會想去做些什麼
So,
だから いっぱいいろんなものに気付けなかったのかもしれないな
或許也正因為如此 才錯過了很多吧
I probably didn't notice many things.
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
虛幻之光
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Fleeting Light
That person could see Youkai.
その人には妖怪が見えた
那個人過去能看見妖怪
They exchanged their feelings and became important to each other.
心を交わし やがて大切な存在になった
兩人真心相待 彼此相愛
でもある日
但是有一天
But one day...
He can't see Ayakashi anymore?
妖の姿が見えなくなったか
他看不到妖怪了嗎
If he is happy, then I don't mind.
あの人が幸せでいるなら
只要那人能獲得幸福
私はかまわない
我無怨無尤
Are you sure,
本当かい キヨ
真的嗎 清
Kio?